Rhiannon: If parents have a good
relationship with their child, they will
usually find that the child is more likely
to open up to them about their problems.
One of the most important ways
parents can help, is to listen to them
and take their feelings seriously.
Leah: Children and young people’s
negative feelings usually pass, but
it’s a good idea to get help and
support if this goes on longer and
their negative feelings are stopping
them from getting on with their lives.
Rhiannon: Especially if their distress
is disrupting family life or if they
are repeatedly behaving in ways that
would not be expected at their age.
Leah: If a child or young person is having
problems at school, a teacher, school
nurse, school counsellor or educational
psychologist may be able to help.
Otherwise parents or
carers can approach a GP.
Professionals are able to refer a
child to further help such as Child and
Adolescent Mental Health Services [CAMHS].
Most support is provided free by
the NHS, the school or a local
council’s social services department.
Rhiannon: Treatments for children and
young people with mental health problems
put a lot of emphasis on talking and
on understanding the problem in order
to work out the best way to tackle it.
For younger children, this
may be done through play.
Leah: Children and young people always
need to be assessed by a specialist
before they are prescribed any medication.
Children and young people can seek
help on their own, if they wish, by
ringing a helpline or approaching a
professional directly, but consent
is usually needed for them to get
medical care if they are under 16.
Rhiannon: Early intervention can
help with children's social and
emotional development including
increasing their social interaction and
behaviour, improving self-esteem and
reducing the incidents of clinically
diagnosed mental health problems.
Leah: Let’s hear from a professional
about how early intervention can help.